Finding Aid for Cornelius L. T. Gabler papers, 1939-1988
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Cornelius L. T. Gabler papers 1939-1988
Gabler, Cornelius L. T., 1902-1988.
1 linear feet
921112 Aa 2
Detroit, Michigan, architect; 1934 graduate of the University of Michigan. Biographical material and descriptions of his architectural work, including photographs; also photographs taken during World War II and report of U.S. Strategic Bombing Survey on Wake Island, Marshall Islands, and Rabaul, New Britain.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received in two accession, in 1992 from Gabler’s sister Nan Sparrow (donor no. 8074 ), and in 1994 from Gabler’s nephew George Sparrow (donor no. 7594 ).
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Cornelius (Neil) Gabler was a Detroit, Michigan, architect who served as a Marine officer in the South Pacific during World War II. He graduated from the University of Michigan College of Architecture and Design in 1934. Among the buildings he designed were the Cooley and Phoenix Memorial Laboratories on the University of Michigan North Campus, and the Penguinarium at the Detroit Zoo. During World War II Gabler served as a Marine Corps aviation and intelligence officer in the South Pacific, and after the Japanese surrender served as intelligence officer for the Marshalls-Gilberts-New Britain Party of the U.S. Strategic Bombing Survey.
A large part of this collection is made up of black and white slides taken during World War II in the South Pacific and color slides taken in 1945 and 1946 during the Strategic Bombing Survey of Wake Island, the Marshall Islands, and Rabaul, New Britain. The collection does not include any information as to whether Gabler was the actual photographer. The slides are identified by a topical code system, which is deciphered as much as possible in this finding aid. Some of the slides are mounted in cardboard mounts and are stored in folders, the rest in glass and metal mounts and stored in a metal box. The finding aid indicates the locations for each topical code.
The book The Allied Campaigns Against Wake Island, the Marshall Islands and Rabaul, New Britain: A Photographic Record, included with the collection, parallels the topics of the slides taken during the Strategic Bombing Survey, but does not duplicate any of the pictures in the slide files.
Subjects:
Architects.; Gabler, Cornelius L. T., 1902-1988.; United States Strategic Bombing Survey.; World War, 1939-1945.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Buildings--Michigan--Detroit.; Campaigns and battles--Oceania.; Detroit (Mich.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Hawaii.; Jaluit Atoll (Marshall Islands); Majuro Atoll (Marshall Islands); Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project.; New Britain Island (Papua New Guinea); Nuclear reactors.; Phoenix Memorial Laboratory.; Recruiting and enlistment.; United States. Marine Corps.; Wake Island.; War casualties.; War damage--Oceania.; World War, 1939-1945.; Wotje Atoll (Marshall Islands)
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Slides.
- Biographical and other materials
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
    (includes World War II service)
  - Resume of professional qualifications (includes photos) (Box 1)
  - "Ideal House" (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - Photographs (unidentified) (Box 1)
    (includes interiors rooms with U-M sports theme and one photo of Cooley Phoenix laboratory construction site.)
- Slides
  - Code C-color slides taken during Strategic Bombing Survey 1945-1946
    - Wake Island, 19 (in box); 43 slides (in folder) (Box 1)
      (C1-C9)
    - Majuro/Mille, 24 (in box); 4 slides (in folder) (Box 1)
      (C10-C16)
    - Wotje, 9 slides (in box) (Box 1)
      (C17-C19)
    - Jaluit, 18 (in box); 6 slides (in folder) (Box 1)
      (C20-C22)
    - Laura, 3 (in box); 13 slides (in folder) (Box 1)
      (C23-C27)
    - Rabaul, 26 (in box); 34 slides (in folder) (Box 1)
      (C28-C45)
    - Johnston Island (Box 1)
      (1 slide in folder)
      (C45)
  - Code C-burials in battlefield cemetery, 3 slides (in folder) black and white (Box 1)
  - Code CP-Cherry Point, N.C 1945, 29 slides (in folder) color (Box 1)
  - Code D-Japanese dead, 13 slides (in folder) black and white (Box 1)
  - Code ED-combat scenes, 3 slides (in folder) black and white (Box 1)
  - Code G-combat scenes, 12 slides (in folder) black and white (Box 1)
  - Code H-of Hawaii circa 1945, 2 (in box); 18 slides (in folder) color (Box 1)
  - Code M-aerial views of an island, 8 slides (in folder) black and white (Box 1)
  - Code N scenery, 4 slides (in folder) black and white (Box 1)
  - Code NC-of military scene, 1 slides (in folder) black and white (Box 1)
  - code NP-river, 1 slides (in folder) black and white (Box 1)
  - Code P-U.S. personnel, mixed with slides of Japanese prisoners, 14 slides (in folder) black and white (Box 1)
  - Code PAB-puppy, 3 slides (in folder) black and white (Box 1)
  - Code PAN-native village and people, 8 slides (in folder) black and white (Box 1)
  - Code R-radar installation?, 7 slides (in folder) black and white (Box 1)
  - Code T-military camp, 1 slides (in folder) black and white (Box 1)
  - Uncoded, 125 (in box); 22 slides (in folder) (Box 1)
  - Marine recruiting-construction of Detroit Marine recruiting station 1942, 29 slides (in folder) color and black and white (Box 1)
- Book
  - The Allied Campaigns Against Wake Island, the Marshall Islands and Rabaul, New Britain: A Photographic Record 1946 (Box 1)